<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Publish>
  <ModId Value="142844" />
  <DisplayName Value="Vanilla Profiler" />
  <ShortDescription Value="In-game frame health, sync-point and memory monitor — find which mod stresses your main thread." />
  <LongDescription>## Vanilla Profiler

Diagnostic mod for Cities: Skylines II. Two audiences in one install — a traffic-light health overlay for normal players, and a main-thread / sync-point / memory analyzer for mod authors and power users.

### For players

- **Status screen** — Good / Warning / Problem with the likely cause and one-line advice
- **Diagnosis screen** — plain-language explanation when something is wrong
- **Memory leak detector** — flags sustained managed-heap growth
- **Bottleneck verdict** — RenderBound / SimBound / MemoryBound / Balanced with concrete next step
- **Auto-screenshots on stutters** — frames over 100 ms get captured to disk
- **Ctrl+F11 support file** — one-click bundle (system info, mods, stats, log tail) to send to mod authors

### For mod authors and power users

- **Per-system main-thread cost** — Stopwatch around every SystemBase.Update separates vanilla vs each mod; assemblies attributed by ModAttribution
- **Sync-point flagging** — Update() calls above the threshold (default 0.5 ms, tunable) tagged "[likely sync point]" in the log; per-system suspect-call counter
- **ECB.Playback timing** — Harmony hook on EntityCommandBuffer.Playback surfaces structural-change cost separately from system Update time
- **GPU/CPU thread breakdown** — Unity ProfilerRecorder for CPU Main / CPU Render / GPU Frame Time (real hardware numbers, not driver-reported)
- **Full 5-second PERF reports** in VanillaProfiler.log — phase tables, top vanilla and mod systems by main-thread time, ECB cost, memory deltas
- **Memory metrics** — managed (GC), Mono heap, native alloc/reserved, GPU driver memory, growth rate per second, baseline delta
- **Harmony conflict detector** — lists methods patched by more than one mod

### Scope of measurement (read this)

Per-system numbers reflect **main-thread cost only** — scheduling overhead, sync points, structural changes, ECB playback, and synchronous main-thread work. Job execution on worker threads is **not** captured: Burst-compiled jobs run as native code outside SystemBase.Update() and cannot be instrumented from a mod. For per-job analysis attach **Unity Profiler** to the running game.

Frame time, GPU frame time, CPU main/render thread time, all memory metrics, frame spike detection and sync-point flagging are accurate.

### Hotkeys

- **Ctrl+F7** — Toggle spike screenshots
- **Ctrl+F8** — Settings panel
- **Ctrl+F9** — Cycle overlay mode (Status → Diagnosis → Details → Hidden)
- **Ctrl+F10** — Force log dump
- **Ctrl+F11** — Create a support file (system info, mods, stats, log tail)
- **Ctrl+F12** — Cycle overlay position

### Output locations

- Continuous log: `Logs/VanillaProfiler.log`
- Diagnostic reports: `Reports/CSII_Report_*.txt`
- Spike screenshots: `Logs/spikes/spike_*.png`
- Settings: `VanillaProfiler/settings.json`

All paths are inside `%LOCALAPPDATA%Low\Colossal Order\Cities Skylines II\`.

### Compatibility

- **Works with any mod combination** — no gameplay changes, no entity creation, no save persistence
- **Read-only ECS queries** — never mutates game state
- **Detects Harmony patch conflicts** — lists methods patched by more than one mod

### Performance overhead

Adds approximately **15 microseconds per frame** from Stopwatch instrumentation across ~300 systems. Negligible compared to the systems being measured.

### How to share a bug report

1. Press **Ctrl+F11** while the lag is happening
2. Find `CSII_Report_*.txt` in your Reports folder
3. Attach it to your bug report — it includes system info, loaded mods, the latest report window, top mods, and the last 50 lines of the perf log</LongDescription>
  <Thumbnail Value="Properties/thumbnail.png" />
  <ModVersion Value="1.4.0" />
  <GameVersion Value="*" />
  <AccessLevel Value="Public" />
  <Tag Value="Code Mod" />
  <ChangeLog>v1.4.0 — sync-point detection and accurate measurement scope
- Per-system numbers now labelled as main-thread cost: scheduling overhead, sync points, structural changes, ECB playback. Burst-compiled jobs running on worker threads are not captured — for per-job analysis use Unity Profiler.
- New: sync-point detection. Per-system Update() calls above SyncPointThresholdMs (default 0.5 ms) are flagged as "[likely sync point]" in the log — these are the real main-thread bottlenecks worth investigating.
- New: ECB.Playback timing. EntityCommandBuffer playback is always main-thread and is now timed separately under Phases.
- New: aggregate worker-thread metrics. When the build exposes the markers, "Job workers" line shows total job execution time and main-thread wait-on-workers per frame (no per-system attribution).
- Renamed report fields: "Top Systems" / "System Time" → "Top Main-Thread Systems" / "Main-Thread Cost" to match what is actually measured.
- Removed GC garbage from MemorySampler and report-builder hot paths (pooled sort buffers, reused ProfilerRecorderSample buffer).
- Log file is now truncated at every game start instead of growing indefinitely — keeps VanillaProfiler.log focused on the current session, never balloons across runs.</ChangeLog>
  <ExternalLink Type="github" Url="https://github.com/Theorist100/VanillaProfiler" />
</Publish>
