<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Publish>
  <ModId Value="142844" />
  <DisplayName Value="Vanilla Profiler" />
  <ShortDescription Value="In-game frame health, sync-point and memory monitor — find which mod stresses your main thread." />
  <LongDescription>## Vanilla Profiler

Diagnostic mod for Cities: Skylines II. Two audiences in one install — a traffic-light health overlay for normal players, and a main-thread / sync-point / memory analyzer for mod authors and power users.

### For players

- **Status screen** — Good / Warning / Problem with the likely cause and one-line advice
- **Diagnosis screen** — plain-language explanation when something is wrong
- **Memory leak detector** — flags sustained managed-heap growth
- **Bottleneck verdict** — RenderBound / SimBound / MemoryBound / Balanced with concrete next step
- **Auto-screenshots on stutters** — frames over 100 ms get captured to disk
- **Ctrl+F11 support file** — one-click bundle (system info, mods, stats, log tail) to send to mod authors

### For mod authors and power users

- **Per-system self main-thread cost** — Stopwatch around every SystemBase.Update separates vanilla vs each mod, subtracts nested system Update time, and keeps inclusive time for diagnostics; assemblies attributed by ModAttribution
- **Sync-point flagging** — Update() calls above the threshold (default 0.5 ms, tunable) tagged "[likely sync point]" in the log; per-system suspect-call counter
- **ECB.Playback timing** — Harmony hook on EntityCommandBuffer.Playback surfaces structural-change cost separately from system Update time
- **GPU/CPU thread breakdown** — Unity ProfilerRecorder for CPU Main / CPU Render / GPU Frame Time (real hardware numbers, not driver-reported)
- **Full 5-second PERF reports** in VanillaProfiler.log — phase tables, top vanilla and mod systems by self main-thread time, inclusive Update context, ECB cost, memory deltas
- **Memory metrics** — managed (GC), Mono heap, native alloc/reserved, GPU driver memory, growth rate per second, baseline delta
- **Harmony conflict detector** — lists methods patched by more than one mod
- **Patched-vanilla detector** — when a mod prefixes a vanilla OnUpdate, surfaces the row "Game.X.YSystem N.N ms ← ModName". Total Update ms is measured unconditionally (independent of the "Profile vanilla systems" toggle); the elapsed time blends the patching mod's prefix with the vanilla original because Harmony does not let us split them, but the total is honest. Listed per cycle in the overlay, the PERF.log report tables, and the Ctrl+F11 export.

### Scope of measurement (read this)

Top per-system numbers reflect **self main-thread cost only** — scheduling overhead, sync points, structural changes, ECB playback, and synchronous main-thread work, with nested SystemBase.Update calls subtracted from the parent. Inclusive/total Update time is still kept for patched-vanilla diagnostics. Job execution on worker threads is **not** captured: Burst-compiled jobs run as native code outside SystemBase.Update() and cannot be instrumented from a mod. For per-job analysis attach **Unity Profiler** to the running game.

Frame time, GPU frame time, CPU main/render thread time, all memory metrics, frame spike detection and sync-point flagging are accurate.

### Hotkeys

- **Ctrl+F7** — Toggle spike screenshots
- **Ctrl+F8** — Settings panel
- **Ctrl+F9** — Cycle overlay mode (Status → Diagnosis → Tips → Details → Engine → Hide)
- **Ctrl+F10** — Force log dump
- **Ctrl+F11** — Create a support file (system info, mods, stats, log tail)
- **Ctrl+F12** — Cycle overlay position

### Output locations

- Continuous log: `Logs/VanillaProfiler.log`
- Diagnostic reports: `Reports/CSII_Report_*.txt`
- Spike screenshots: `Logs/spikes/spike_*.png`
- Settings: `VanillaProfiler/settings.json`

All paths are inside `%LOCALAPPDATA%Low\Colossal Order\Cities Skylines II\`.

### Compatibility

- **Works with any mod combination** — no gameplay changes, no entity creation, no save persistence
- **Read-only ECS queries** — never mutates game state
- **Detects Harmony patch conflicts** — lists methods patched by more than one mod

### Performance overhead

Adds approximately **15 microseconds per frame** from Stopwatch instrumentation across ~300 systems. Negligible compared to the systems being measured.

### How to share a bug report

1. Press **Ctrl+F11** while the lag is happening
2. Find `CSII_Report_*.txt` in your Reports folder
3. Attach it to your bug report — it includes system info, loaded mods, the latest report window, top mods, and the last 50 lines of the perf log</LongDescription>
  <Thumbnail Value="Properties/thumbnail.png" />
  <ModVersion Value="1.5.1" />
  <GameVersion Value="*" />
  <AccessLevel Value="Public" />
  <Tag Value="Code Mod" />
  <ChangeLog>Top Mods and Top Systems now report self/exclusive main-thread cost, so nested SystemBase.Update calls are no longer double-counted. Numbers can be lower than previous releases; that is expected and more mathematically correct.
VanillaProfiler.log now shows SELF and INCL columns for system tables. Patched-vanilla rows still use total Update ms because the prefix/original split is not measurable.
Replacement detection now uses a deduplicated per-Type snapshot refreshed at lifecycle boundaries and at the start of each report window, so patched-vanilla routing and report output read the same state.
Session lifecycle resets now initialize correctly when the mod is reloaded inside an already loaded city, and long pauses reset memory-growth history instead of producing false leak spikes.</ChangeLog>
  <ExternalLink Type="github" Url="https://github.com/Theorist100/VanillaProfiler" />
</Publish>
